17 chapter 18 of Black Beauty this LibriVox recording is in the public
domain Black Beauty by Anna Su chapter 18 Going for the
Doctor One night, a few days after James had left, I had eaten my hay and was
lying down in my straw fast asleep, when I was suddenly roused by the stable bell
ringing very loud. I heard the door of Jon's house open, and his feet running up
to the hall. He was back again in no time; he unlocked the stable door, and came in,
calling out, “Wake up, Beauty! You must go well now, if ever you
did;” and almost before I could think he had got the saddle on my back and the
bridle on my head. He just ran round for his coat, and then took me at a quick
trot up to the hall door. The squire stood there, with a lamp
in his hand. “Now, John,” he said, “ride for your life— —that is, for your mistress's
life; there is not a moment to lose. Give this note to Dr. White; give your horse a
rest at the inn, and be back as soon as you
can Jon said, “Yes, sir I was on my back in a
minute. The gardener who lived at the lodge had heard the bell ring, and was
ready with the gate open, and away we went through the park, and through the
village, and down the hill till we came to the toall gate John called very loud
and thumped upon the door; the man was soon out and flung open the gate. “Now,”
said John, “do you keep the gate open for the doctor; here's the money,” and off he went
again. There was before us a long piece of level road by the Riverside John said
to me, “Now, Beauty, do your best,” and so I
did; I wanted no whip or spur, and for two
miles I galloped as fast as I could lay my feet to the ground; I don't believe
that my old grandfather, who won the race at New Market could have gone
faster. When we came to the bridge John pulled me up a little and patted my neck.
“Well done, Beauty! good old fellow,” he said. He would have let me go slower, but
my spirit was up, and I was off again as fast as
before. The air was frosty, the moon was bright; it was very pleasant.
We came through a village, then through a dark wood, then uphill, then downhill, till
after 8 miles' run we came to the town, through the streets and into the
marketplace It was all quite still except the clatter of my feet on the stones— —everybody was
asleep. The church clock struck 3 as we drew up at Dr. White's door. John rang the
bell twice, and then knocked at the door like thunder. A window was thrown up, and Dr.
White, in his night cap put his head out and said, “What do you want?” “Mrs. Gordon is
very ill, sir; master wants you to go at once; he thinks she will die if you
cannot get there. Here is a note.” “Wait,” he said, “I will
come.” He shut the window, and was soon at
the door. “The worst of it is,” he said, “that
my horse has been out all day and is quite done up; my son has just been sent
for, and he has taken the other. What is to be done? Can I have your
horse?” “He has comeing to gallop nearly all the way, sir, and I was to give him a
rest here; but I think my master would not be against it, if you think fit, sir.”
“All right,” he said; “I will soon be ready JN stood by me and stroked my neck;
I was very hot. The doctor came out with his riding whip You need not take that,
sir,” said John; “Black Beauty will go until he drops. Take care of him, sir, if you can;
I should not like any harm to come to him.” “No, no, John,” said the doctor, “I hope
not,” and in a minute we had left Jon far behind. I will not tell about our way
back. The doctor was a heavier man than John, and not so good a rider; however, I
did my very best. The man at the Tollgate had it
open. When we came to the hill the doctor drew me up. “Now, my good fellow,” he said,
“take some breath.” I was glad he did, for I was nearly spent,
but that breathing helped me on, and soon we were in the park. Joe was at the lodge
gate; my master was at the hall door, for he had heard us coming. He spoke not a
word; the doctor went into the house with him, and Joe led me to the
stable. I was glad to get home; my legs shook under me, and I could only stand
and pant. I had not a dry hair on my body,
the water ran down my legs, and I steamed
all over Joey used to say, like a pot on the
fire. Poor Joe! he was young and small, and as yet he knew very little, and his
father, who would have helped him, had been sent to the next village; but I am
sure he did the very best he knew. He rubbed my legs and my chest, but he did
not put my warm cloth on me; he thought I
was so hot I should not like it. Then he
gave me a pale full of water to drink; it
was cold and very good, and I drank it all; then he gave me some hay and some
corn, and thinking he had done right, he went away. Soon I began to shake and tremble,
and turned deadly cold; my legs achd my loins achd and my chest achd and I felt
sore all over. Oh! how I wished for my warm, thick
cloth, as I stood and trembled. I wished
for John, but he had 8 miles to walk, so I
lay down in my straw and tried to go to sleep
sleep After a long while I heard Jon at
the door; I gave a low moan, for I was in
great pain. He was at my side in a moment,
stooping down by me. I could not tell him
how I felt, but he seemed to know it all;
he covered me up with two or three warm cloths, and then ran to the house for
some hot water; he made me some warm grel
which I drank, and then I think I went to sleep. John seemed to be very much put
out. I heard him say to himself over and over again, “Stupid boy! stupid boy! no
cloth put on, and I dare say the water was cold, too; boys are no good;” but Joe
was a good boy, after all. I was now very ill; a strong
inflammation had attacked my lungs, and I could not draw my breath without pain.
John nursed me night and day; he would get up two or three times in the night
to come to me. My master, too, often came
to see me. “My poor Beauty,” he said one day, “my good horse, you saved your mistress's
life, Beauty; yes, you saved her life.” I was very glad to hear that, for it
seems the doctor had said if we had been a little longer it would have been too
late. John told my master he never saw a horse go so fast in his life. It seemed
as if the horse knew what was the matter. Of course I did, though John
thought what not; at least I knew as much
as this— —that JN and I must go at the top
of our speed, and that it was for the sake of the
mistress end of chapter